Inventory to the United States. Military Mission to Armenia. Photographs, 1919
Hoover Institution Archives
United States. Military Mission to Armenia. Photographs,
1919
XX037
United States. Military Mission to Armenia
1 manuscript box 0.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Depicts American army officers in Armenia, and conditions in Armenia at the end of World War I
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States. Army--Pictorial works; Armenia (Republic)--History--Pictorial works; Armenia (Republic); Soviet Union; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920--Pictorial works; United States--Armed Forces; Turkey
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection consists of 94 prints taken during the United States fact-finding military mission to Turkey and Armenia (1919), headed by General Harbord appointed and by President Wilson on the advice of Herbert Hoover.
The photographs were taken from September 8, 1919, when General Harbord and his party arrived at Izmit Bay, Turkey, through October 9, 1919, when they came aboard the U.S.S. "Martha Washington" in Batumi, Georgia. They depict General Harbord and other members of the mission, Turkish and Armenian political figures, including Mustafa Kamal Pasha (Kamal Pasha Atatürk, future president of the Republic of Turkey) and Alexander Khatissian, prime minister of Armenia, with members of his cabinet; urban and rural views in Armenia and Turkey; national dances, etc.
The prints were arranged by the collector in chronological order, and each print was assigned a unique number from 67280 through 67373. An inventory, arranged by print number, was included in the collection.
This finding aid follows the original arrangement and description of the photographs, though geographical names and some personal names are presented in accordance with the current spelling. It should be noted that some geographical locations listed as located on the territory of Armenia (Kars, Sarikamis) in 1921 were returned to Turkey in accordance with the Treaty of Kars between the Bolsheviks and the Republic of Turkey.
Inventory
- Captured German cruiser Goeben at Bay of Izmit, Turkey. This cruiser is being guarded by an English cruiser. September 8, 1919., 67280 (Folder A)
- View of English cruiser guarding the captured Goeben, at Bay of Izmit, Turkey. September 8, 1919., 67281
- View of Izmit, Turkey. September 8, 1919., 67282 (Folder A)
- Armenians greeting General Harbord at Izmit, Turkey. September 8, 1919., 67283 (Folder A)
- Winnowing wheat at Alayund, Turkey. September 9, 1919., 67284 (Folder A)
- Winnowing wheat at Alayund, Turkey. September 9, 1919., 67285 (Folder A)
- View of Afion Karahissar (Afiyonkarahisar), Turkey. September 9, 1919., 67286 (Folder A)
- Showing method the natives use in preserving the straw left after the wheat has been threshed. This straw is used for fodder; also mixed with clay in brickmaking and with manure for fuel. September 10, 1919., 67287 (Folder A)
- Typical beggar in Turkey, this was taken at Oulu Kichla (probably Ki$#015f;la, Bolu province), Turkey. September 10, 1919., 67288 (Folder A)
- View from old stone bridge over the River Seyhan at Adana, Turkey. September 11, 1919., 67289 (Folder A)
- Transportation methods. Donkeys and carts coming over the bridge at Adana, Turkey, crossing the Seyhan River. September 11, 1919., 67290
- Same as the above., 67291 (Folder B)
- Transportation methods in Turkey. Carts being drawn by water buffalo over the bridge at Adana, Turkey, crossing the Seyhan River. September 11, 1919., 67292 (Folder B)
- Street scene in Adana, Turkey. September 11, 1919., 67293 (Folder B)
- Arabs who paid us a visit at Ras el Ain, Turkey. September 12, 1919., 67294 (Folder B)
- View of the City of Mardin, Turkey. September 14, 1919., 67295 (Folder B)
- Reception party to receive General Harbord's party to Mardin. From left to right: Salath Effendi, Station Master; Maxim Bey, of the Police; Issac Effendi, City Councilman; Abdul Rizal, Police Commissioner; Ali Riza Repr, Military Commander; Shukir Bey, Commander of the Gendarmes; Abdul Rahman Cheleke, Councilman; Miss Agnes Fenanga, of the American Committee for Relief in the Near East; Nezib Effendi, Vice Mayor; and Captain S.G. Dudley, of the American Committee for Relief in the Near East. September 13, 1919., 67296 (Folder B)
- Scene taken in Mardin, Turkey. Notice wind mill in background, resembling Dutch wind mill September 14, 1919., 67297 (Folder B)
- Typical small town in the interior of Turkey; taken outside of Mardin, Turkey. September 15, 1919., 67298 (Folder B)
- From right to left: Generals Moseley, Harbord, and McCoy. At small village out from Mardin, Turkey, showing detachment of Turkish soldiers in background. September 15, 1919., 67299 (Folder B)
- Generals Harbord, Moseley, and McCoy talking with Professor Hussein Bey and General Kenan Bey, Commander of Turkish Division, between Mardin and Diyarbakir. September 15, 1919, Khanik, Turkey., 67300
- General Harbord reviewing Turkish troops drawn up to receive him outside of the city of Diyarbakir. September 15, 1919., 67301 (Folder C)
- Scene in Diyarbakir, Turkey, showing market place and autos belonging to General Harbord's party. September 15, 1919., 67302 (Folder C)
- Interior of large courtyard in Diyarbakir, Turkey. September 15, 1919., 67303 (Folder C)
- Typical graveyard, taken outside of the city of Diyarbakir, Turkey. September 15, 1919., 67304 (Folder C)
- View of the valley before dropping down into Harput. September 16, 1919., 67305 (Folder C)
- Bad place for the cars to get over at a crossing near the Euphrates River. September 18, 1919., 67306 (Folder C)
- Same as above., 67307 (Folder C)
- Same as above., 67308 (Folder C)
- Generals Harbord and Moseley inspecting an Arabs rifle. September 18, 1919., 67309 (Folder C)
- Gorge on the Euphrates River. September 18, 1919., 67310
- Generals Harbord, McCoy, and Moseley, talking with Professor Hussein Bey and Kenan Bey, General of the Turkish Division at Mardin. At camp on the Tohma Su River. September 19, 1919., 67311 (Folder D)
- View of camp on the Tohma Su River. September 19, 1919., 67312 (Folder D)
- Town of Hassan Çelebi and surrounding country. September 19, 1919., 67313 (Folder D)
- Methods of travel in Turkey. A donkey caravan on the road from Diyarbakir to Sivas. September 19, 1919., 67314 (Folder D)
- Threshing wheat near Hassan Çelebi, Turkey. September 19, 1919., 67315 (Folder D)
- Street scene in the village of Kangal, Turkey. September 19, 1919., 67316 (Folder D)
- View of Alkali Lake near Sivas, Turkey. September 20, 1919., 67317 (Folder D)
- View of Sivas and valley taken from the road to Diyarbakir. September 20, 1919., 67318 (Folder D)
- Moustapha Kemal Pasha, the Turkish general who defended the Dardanelles. Taken at Sivas, Turkey. September 21, 1919., 67319 (Folder D)
- Moustapha Kemal Pasha and Raouf Bey, Sivas, Turkey. September 21, 1919., 67320
- Group of Turkish officials at Sivas, Turkey. From left to right, sitting: Rustem Bey; Raif Effendi; Moustpha Kemal Pasha; Raouf Bey; Hadji Faizi Effendi; standing: Bekir Samu Bey; Sureya Bey; Husrev Samu Bey; Omar Mumtaz Bey; Thsan Bey; Mazhar Mufid Bey; Vassif Bey.September 21, 1919., 67321 (Folder E)
- View of mountain roads passed over by General Harbord's party from Sivas to Erzincan, Turkey, September, 22, 1919., 67322 (Folder E)
- View of mountains near Erzincan, Turkey, September 22, 1919., 67323 (Folder E)
- View of courthouse and sign advocating the 12th article of Wilson's, Fourteen points at Erzincan, Turkey. September 23, 1919., 67324 (Folder E)
- Turkish orphans at orphanage at Erzincan, Turkey. September 23, 1919., 67325 (Folder E)
- General Harbord being received at Mamahatun (Teçan), Turkey. September 24, 1919., 67326 (Folder E)
- Natives of Mamahatun (Teçan), Turkey. September 24, 1919., 67327 (Folder E)
- Officers of the 14th Turkish Army Corps waiting to receive General Harbord's party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67328 (Folder E)
- Boys from the Turkish orphanage at Erzurum waiting for the coming of General Harbord's party to Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67329 (Folder E)
- Turkish Cavalry of the 15th Turkish Army Corps, at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67330
- General Harbord being received at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67331 (Folder F)
- Same as above., 67332 (Folder F)
- Same as above., 67333 (Folder F)
- Turkish orphan boy handing General Harbord bouquet at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67334 (Folder F)
- Natives at Erzurum, Turkey, waiting to see General Harbord and his party. Showing methods of dress, etc. September 25, 1919., 67335 (Folder F)
- Nejati Bey addressing General Harbord and officers at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67336 (Folder F)
- Lazi Dancer from Trabzon district dancing at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67337 (Folder F)
- Turkish women watching the sports at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67338 (Folder F)
- Same as above., 67339 (Folder F)
- Wrestlers at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67340
- Native dancers dancing at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67341 (Folder G)
- A sign advocating the 12th Article of Wilson's Fourteen points at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67342 (Folder G)
- Sword dancers at the reception given for General Harbord and party at Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67343 (Folder G)
- Old Turkish gate and minarets in Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67344 (Folder G)
- Method of shoeing oxen, taken in Erzurum, Turkey. September 25, 1919., 67345 (Folder G)
- An old castle on the road from Erzurum, Turkey, to Kars, Armenia. September 26, 1919., 67346 (Folder G)
- Russian Church in Sarikamis, Armenia, showing style of Russian Architecture. September 27, 1919., 67347 (Folder G)
- Armenian cavalry acting as guard for General Harbord and party at Kars, Armenia. The picture was taken as the party was leaving the Governor's house after a dinner given to them by the Governor of Kars.September 27, 1919., 67348 (Folder G)
- Old Fort at Kars, Armenia, overlooking the city of Kars. September 27, 1919., 67349 (Folder G)
- Old Armenian church built in 1624 at Echmiadzin, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67350
- Armenian orphans waiting to see General Harbord at Echmiadzin, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67351 (Folder H)
- General Harbord and officers entering courtyard at Echmiadzin, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67352 (Folder H)
- Camels and drivers with Mt. Ararat in background. September 29, 1919., 67353 (Folder H)
- Camels and drivers out from Yerevan, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67354 (Folder H)
- General Harbord and the Armenian Bishop Gevork Surenian at Echmiadzin, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67355 (Folder H)
- Shah Hatoomi, Commander of Yerevan, and Captain G.F. Gracey, of the British High Commission, at Yerevan, Armenia. September 29, 1919., 67356 (Folder H)
- Reception committee for General Harbord and party at Yerevan. September 29, 1919., 67357 (Folder H)
- Showing old Persian wall around the city of Yerevan and the bridge across the Zangi (Hrazdan) River. October 1, 1919., 67358 (Folder H)
- Armenian soldiers bringing in prisoners who deserted from the Armenian army, Yerevan, Armenia. October 1, 1919., 67359 (Folder H)
- Scene taken from the priest's palace, Yerevan, Armenia, showing the valley of the Zangi (Hrazdan) River and Mt. Ararat in distance. Probably October 1, 1919., 67360
- Same as above., 67361 (Folder I)
- The GÖy mescid, Blue Persian Mosque, at Yerevan, Armenia. October 1, 1919., 67362 (Folder I)
- The building of the Prime Minister or President of the Armenian Republic, Yerevan, Armenia. Oct. 1, 1919., 67363 (Folder I)
- General Harbord and A. Khatissian, Prime Minister of the Armenian Republic. Taken at Yerevan, capital of the Armenian Republic. October 1, 1919., 67364 (Folder I)
- Same as the above., 67365 (Folder I)
- The Cabinet of the Armenian Republic. From left to right, sitting: A. Sahakian, Agriculture; A. Khatissian, Prime Minister; General K. Araradian, War Minister; standing: N. Aghbanian, Education; A. Gulkandanian; Interior Justice; S. Araradian, Finance. Taken at Yerevan, Armenia. October 1, 1919., 67366 (Folder I)
- View of Yerevan, Capital of Armenian Republic, showing Mt. Ararat in a distance. October 1, 1919., 67367 (Folder I)
- Same as above., 67368 (Folder I)
- Lt. Khatchadoorian and Shah Hatoomi, Commander of Yerevan. Taken at Yerevan, Armenia. October 1, 1919., 67369 (Folder I)
- Refugees and baggage waiting to come aboard the Martha Washington at Batumi, Georgia. October 8, 1919., 67370 (Folder I)
- Street scene in Batumi, Georgia. October. 8, 1919., 67371 (Folder J)
- Harbor of Trabzon and the U.S.S. Martha Washington in harbor (the last boat to the right). October 9, 1919., 67372 (Folder J)
- View of Trabzon, Turkey, from the U.S.S. Martha Washington. Oct. 9, 1919., 67373 (Folder J)